Register of the Yves Jean Antoine Noël Godard papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Yves Jean Antoine Noël Godard papers,
1929-1974
76073
Hoover Institution Archives
13 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 envelope (6.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, messages, reports, dossiers, maps, photographs, clippings, and speeches and writings relating to military and resistance operations during World War II, military operations during the Indochinese War, and military, police, and terrorist activities during the Algerian independence struggle. Includes records of the Armée secrète de Haute-Savoie.
Godard, Yves Jean Antoine Noël, 1911-1975
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1911, December 21 Born, Saint Maixent, France
1929 Baccalauréat, Faculté des Sciences, Université de Strasbourg
1932 Graduated from the Ecole Spéciale Militaire de Saint-Cyr (military academy); sous-lieutenant, 27th Bataillon de Chasseurs Alpins (Alpine Infantry)
1937 Champion de France militaire de ski (military ski champion)
1939 Member, French military mission to Poland
1940 Captain; captured by German forces, June 16, at Maizières, France
1940-1944 Prisoner of war (Oflag 10, Montwy, Poland); escaped to France via Germany disguised as a Spanish laborer
1944 Battalion chief, 27th Bataillon de Chasseurs Alpins; commander of the Armée Secrète de Haute-Savoie (Secret Army of Resistance Fighters of Haute-Savoie)
1945-1948 Occupation duty in Austria
1948-1952 Commander of the 11th Bataillon de Choc (Special Forces)
1952-1955 Duty in Indochina; commander of the Groupement Mobile Nord of the Forces Terrestres du Laos (combined French and Laotian forces); attempted to relieve the siege of Dien Bien Phu; lieutenant colonel
1955-1957 Adjutant to General Massu, commander of the 10th Division Parachutiste (Paratroop Division); commander of the Algiers-Sahel military sector; active role in the "Battle of Algiers"; colonel
1958-1960 Directeur général de la Sûreté Nationale en Algérie (director of police)
1960-1961 Adjutant in the subdivision of Nevers, France
1961 Participant in the April putsch in Algeria; condemned to death in absentia
1961-1962 Organizer and chief of intelligence of the O.A.S. (Organisation Armée Secrète) in Algeria
1965-1975 Manufacturer, Papignies, Belgium
1972 Author, Les Paras dans la ville (Paratroops in the City), vol. I of Les Trois Batailles d'Alger (The Three Battles of Algiers) (Paris: Librairie Arthème Fayard)
1975, March 3 Died, Lessines, Belgium
Armée secrète de Haute-Savoie.; France. Armée--Officers.; Organisation Armée secrète.; Africa.; Algeria--History--Revolution, 1954-1962.; Algeria.; France.; Haute-Savoie (France); Indochinese War, 1946-1954.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945.
- MILITARY CAREER MEMORABILIA, 1930-1948 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, orders, diplomas, certificates, military newspapers, postcards, song sheets, news clippings, maps, invitations, menus, notes, memoranda, reports, and other printed matter and memorabilia, assembled in scrapbook fashion by Godard during his career in the 27th Bataillon de Chasseurs Alpins (Battalion of Alpine Infantry) and the Armée Secrète de Haute-Savoie (Secret Army of Resistance Fighters of Haute-Savoie). Arranged chronologically by year with selected citations to material in which Godard figures prominently.
- ARCHIVES OF THE ARMEE SECRETE DE HAUTE-SAVOIE (FORCES FRANCAISES DE L'INTERIEUR), 1944-1946 (Box 1-2)
  Orders, messages, memoranda, reports, histories, maps, personnel records, and financial correspondence related to the activities of the Secret Army of Resistance Fighters of Haute-Savoie (French forces of the Interior) in the Alpine departments of France during the Resistance. Arranged as listed by subseries.
- INDOCHINA FILE, 1953-1974 (Box 2)
  Reports, orders, messages, maps, balance sheets, news clippings, aerial reconnaissance photos, and a speech and writing related to the activities of French military forces (Forces Terrestres du Laos/Groupement Mobile Nord) in Laos and Tonkin (Vietnam), 1953-1954. Arranged alphabetically by subseries.
- ALGERIA AND FRANCE, 1954-1973 (Box 3-13)
  Chronologies, conference papers, correspondence, orders, messages, reports, dossiers, maps, news clippings, government news journals, newsletters, writings, and miscellaneous notes ephemera, and printed matter dealing with the Algerian independence struggle with France, and in particular with the activities of French military and police forces, the F.L.N. (Front de Libération Nationale/National Liberation Front), and the O.A.S. (Organisation Armée Secrète/Secret Army Organization), written and collected by Godard in his role as an army officer, police official, member of the O.A.S., and interested party. Arranged alphabetically by subseries.
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL (Box 14)
  Maps of North Africa, Algeria, Algiers, Oran, Constantine, etc. (annotated) and a schematic plan of Algiers (annotated) separated from the rest of the Algeria and France materials due to their size.
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Oversize photo file)
  See photo file card index.
- MILITARY CAREER MEMORABILIA, 1930-1948
  - 1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931
  - 1932
  - 1933
  - 1934
  - 1937
  - 1938
  - 1939
  - 1940
    - General
    - "Rapport sur les opérations auxquelles le 27e B.C.A. a participé du 2 septembre 1939 à l'armistice" (Report on military operations in which the 27th Battalion of Alpine Infantry participated from September 2, 1939 until the Armistice), typewritten, 13 pages, circa October
    - Mazaud, Chef de Bataillon, "Quelques faits d'armes du 27e B.C.A. du 5 au 8 juin 1940 (Exploits of the 27th Battalion of Alpine Infantry, June 5-8, 1940), typewritten, 8 pages
  - 1941
    - General
    - Proposition pour la Croix de Chevalier de la Légion d'Honneur en faveur de Capitaine Godard (Yves) du 27ème B.C.A. (Recommendation for the Knight's Cross of the Legion of Honor for Captain Yves Godard of the 27th Battalion of Alpine Infantry), submitted by Battalion Chief Mazaud, Aix-en-Province, September 20
    - Mazaud, Lieutenant-Colonel, Les Diables Bleus du 27me B.C.A. dans la Campagne de France 1939-1940 (The Blue Devils of the 27th Battalion of Alpine Infantry during the Battle of France, 1939-1940), printed, 142 pages
  - 1944
    - General
    - Piat, Phillipe, "Evasion - Mars 1944" (Escape from Poland! March 1944), typewritten (carbon copy), 6 pages
    - Koenig, Phillipe, "Récit de notre évasion d'un oflag de Pologne" (Our Escape from Prison Camp in Poland), typewritten (carbon copy), 9 pages
  - 1945
  - 1946
  - 1947
  - 1948
    - Godard, Yves, "Le 27e B.C.A. Bataillon d'Annecy et de la Haute-Savoie," in Plaquette editée par le Comité des Fêtes d'Annecy en honneur du retour du 27e B.C.A. (Booklet compiled by the Festivities Committee of Annecy in honor of the return of the 27th Battalion of Alpine Infantry from occupation duty in Austria), printed, 2 pages
  - Undated
    - General
    - Etat nominatif des officiers, sous-officiers, caporaux et chasseurs de la C.C. (List of the members of the 27th Battalion of Alpine Infantry), circa 1945-1948
    - Godard, Yves, "Le 27e Bataillon de Chaseurs Alpins et la Résistance en Haute-Savoie, 1940-1944" (The 27th Battalion of Alpine Infantry and the Resistance Movement in Haute-Savoie), typewritten (carbon copy), 7 pages, circa 1946-1948
- ARCHIVES OF THE ARMEE SECRETE DE HAUTE-SAVOIE (FORCES FRANCAISES DE L'INTERIEUR), 1944-1946
  - Orders, messages, and mission reports
    - Organization and mobilization plans, 1944 June-July
    - Parachute drop operation on the Plateau de Glieres, 1944 August 1
    - Organizational plans and intelligence reports, 1944 August 6-13
    - Operation and individual mission orders of the A.S. (Armée Secrète) and the F.T.P. (Francs-Tireurs et Partisans de France), 1944 August 12
    - Liberation of the Département de Haute-Savoie and surrounding areas
      - 1944 August 12-19
      - 1944 August 19-September 9
  - Summary reports and notes (Box 2)
    - General
    - "Essai de synthèse sur les opérations des F.F.I. de Haute-Savoie en Haute-Savoie et en Savoie du 14 au 31 août 1944" (Essay on the operations of the French Forces of the Interior of Haute-Savoie in Haute-Savoie and Savoie, August 14-31, 1944), prepared by Lieutenant Garolet on the basis of reports by unit and sector commanders, typewritten, 18 pages with map, circa Setember 1944-1945
    - Godard, Yves
      - "Rapport succint du Chef de Bataillon Godard, commandant le 27e Bataillon de Chasseurs Alpins, sur le rôle du Bataillon dans la résistance de Haute-Savoie" (Report on the Activities of the 27th Battalion of Alpine Infantry in the Resistance), typewritten, 3 pages, 1945 January 22
      - "Notice historique du 27e B.C.A. pendant la période du 27 novembre 1942 au 30 novembre 1944" (Brief History of the 27th Battalion of Alpine Infantry from November 27, 1942 to November 30, 1944), typewritten (carbon copy), 4 pages, 1945 March 5
  - Personnel records
    - Lists of members of the Armée Secrète, lost, killed, or wounded (perts - tués - blessés), 1944
    - Recommendations for promotions (avancement et nominations), 1944
    - Recommendations for awards, citations, and medals, 1944-1945
    - Recommendations for medals (posthumous), 1944-1945
    - Letters of verification (certificats et attestations) of military service, aid to the Armée Secrète, wounds, and deaths, 1944-1946
    - Miscellaneous
      Includes declassified records returned to file after July 2015 release by Hoover.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence related to the finances of the Armée Secrète, 1944-1946
- INDOCHINA FILE, 1953-1974
  - Aerial reconnaissance photos (see Photographs) (Box 2)
  - Map (annotated)
  - News clippings, French-language press, 1954
  - Reports on French military operations in Laos and Tonkin (Vietnam), 1954
    - "Opération Dampierre," report by Lieutenant-Colonel Godard on the conduct of the 1st Bataillon Parachutistes Laotiens (Laotian Paratroop Battalion), typewritten (carbon copy), 7 pages, 1953 October 15
    - "Opération Drome," report by Lieutenant-Colonel Godard on operations against enemy rebels in Laos, typewritten (carbon copy), 10 pages, 1953 December-1954 February
    - "Opération Condor/Albatros (8 avril-24 mai 1954): Compte rendu d'opération du Groupement Mobile Nord" (Operation "Condor/Albatros" April 8-May 24, 1954: An Account of the Activities of the North Mobile Group of the Land Forces of Laos (Forces Terrestres du Laos) in its attempt to lift the siege of Dien Bien Phu), report prepared by Lieutenant Colonel Godard, commandant of the Groupement Mobile Nord, typewritten (carbon copy), 31 pages, 1954 June
      Accompanied by orders, messages, maps, and supplementary reports on communications, casualties, and provisions, arranged and numbered by Godard.
    - "Compte d'emploi des fonds remis au Lt-Colonel Godard commandant le Groupement Opérationnel du 24-11-53 au 20-7-54" (Balance Sheet of Funds used by Godard in Operations "Ardeche," "Drome," "Chateauneuf," "Condor," "Albatros," and "Bassac," carried out from November 1953 to July 1954), typewritten (carbon copy), 4 pages, 1954 July 28
    - Battle of Koung Rip, summary reports and diagrams sent to Godard, May-July 1954, 1954 May 9
  - Speeches and writings of Yves Godard
    - Address on experiences in Indochina prepared for a conference of the Rotary Club d'Ath, Ath, Belgium, holograph notes, 13 pages. Annotated offprint of prologue from Godard's Les Paras dans la Ville; 35 pages, 1974 March 5
  - Miscellaneous orders and messages
- ALGERIA AND FRANCE, 1954-1973
  - Chronologies, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Conference papers on Algerian affairs prepared by the Corps des Officiers des Affaires Militaires Musulmanes, circa 1954-1955
    - Bretaudeau, Lieutenant, "Géographie de l'Algérie" (Geography of Algeria)
    - Girard-Reydet, Capitaine, "Histoire de l'Algérie jusqu'à 1830" (History of Algeria to 1830)
    - Reynaud, Lieutenant, "L'Algérie de 1830 à 1947" (Algeria from 1830 to 1947)
    - Bouras, Capitaine, "Les Genres de vie en Algérie" (The Modes of Life in Algeria)
    - Pruvot, Capitaine, "Les Institutions Sociales" (Social Institutions)
    - Ciavaldini, Capitaine, "L'Islam" (Islam)
    - Petit, Commandant, "La Femme Musulmane" (The Female Muslim) and "Les Confréries Religieuses" (Religious Fraternities)
    - Corbel, Capitaine, "Le Statut de l'Algérie" (Algerian Law)
    - Sigwarth, Capitaine, "Réalisations dans le domaine économique" (Economic Accomplishments)
    - Salleras, Capitaine, "Les Réalisations Sociales en Algérie (Social Accomplishments)
    - Guinebault, Capitaine, "La Justice" (Justice)
    - Lesourd, Capitaine Michel, "Immigration en Métropole" (Immigration to Metropolitan France)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1973
  - Documents and dossiers on terrorism and counterterrorism, circa 1955-1959
    - Correspondence, messages, and directives, 1957-1959
      - General
      - Massu, General Jacques, directive with annexes and cover letter, 1959 May 24
        "Directive Générale sur La Guerre Subversive" (General Directive on Subversive Warfare), February 24, 1959, typewritten copy, 9 pages.
        Annex on "La Technique Militaire" (Military Technique), May 15, 1959, typewritten copy, 6 pages.
        Annex on "La Technique Psychologique" (Psychological Technique), March 24, 1959, typewritten copy, 4 pages.
    - Reports on French military operations, 1956-1958
      - General
      - "Opération 962," south of Guelma, 1956 March
      - "Opération 837," Nord-Constantinois, 1956 April 30-May 4
      - "Opération Djedida," Nementchas, 1956 June 9-13
      - "Contre-Terrorisme Alger" (Anti-terrorism campaign in Algiers), 1957 January-March
      - "Opération Agounennda," Massif blidéen, 1957 May 23-26
      - "Contre-Terrorisme Alger" (Anti-terrorism campaign in Algiers), 1957 July-August
      - "Réseau Militants 'District'" (Case study of a "district" on the F.L.N. organization in Algiers), circa 1957
    - "Police des Renseignements Généraux d'Alger. Le Terrorisme: Ses origines, ses manifestations, ses conséquences" (Polic report on terrorism), prepared by Carcenac, commissaire divisionnaire, Préfecture d'Alger, mimeograph, 130 pages plus 4 inserts; annex of photographs, 32 pages, circa 1955 January
    - "Organisation des Bandes Rebelles" (Report on the organization of rebel groups), prepared by the Délégation Générale du Gouvernement, Commandement en Chef des Forces en Algérie, Commandement Supérieur Interarmées pour la 10e Région Militaire, Etat-Major-2e Bureau, mimeograph, 145 pages plus map, 1958 July 15
    - "Documents extraits des archives du Secteur Alger-Sahel destinés à éclairer l'opinion sur le vrai visage de l'action repressive et sur les objectifs, les moyens et les methodes de la rébellion" (Documents from the Records of the Algiers-Sahel Military Sector, selected to clarify opinion about the repression of terrorism and the objectives, the means and the methods utilized by the terrorists), prepared by Colonel Godard, adjoint au Général Commandant la 10e D.P. (Paratroop Division) et Commandant le Secteur Alger-Sahel, Algiers, mimeograph, 28 pages, 1958 May 1
    - Dossiers
      - General
      - Abdeliquat, Madame (Ait Saada)
      - Aissat, Idir
      - Ali La Pointe (Ammar Ali)
      - Armée de Libération Nationale (A.L.N.)
      - Audin, Maurice
      - Bengana, Mohamed bel-Hadj (Hamma) and Ahmed Bey
      - Benhamida, Abderrahmane ("Salim"; "El Khiam") (Box 4)
      - Bensmaine, Mimi
      - Bouhired, Djamila
      - Dahimene Sid Ahmed
      - Drif, Zohra
      - Fares, Abderrahmane and Baujard
      - Frances, Jeanne-Marie
      - Front de Libération Nationale (F.L.N.)
      - Hadj-Ali, Bachu
      - Hadj Smaine, Mohamed el Hadi ("Kamel")
      - Hamdiken, Fatima
      - Hattab, Mohamed ("Habib, Rèda")
      - Libéraux-Progressistes (Synthèse sur la collusion de certains milieux européens avec le F.L.N. et le P.C.A.)
      - Minne, Danielle
      - Ouzegane, Amar (Abdel Madjid) and Ouzegane, Fattouma
      - Palladium Chaussures (Argenteuil)
      - Peschard, Raymonde
      - Résistance Algérienne
      - Salem-Alleg
      - Sefta, Ahmed
      - Skandar, Nourredine
      - Tillion, Germaine
      - Yacef, Saadi
  - News clippings, Algerian and French newspapers, journals, and magazines, circa 1955-1974
    - General - Recueil des Journaux d'Algérie,, collection of news clippings from Algerian newspapers reproduced in two bound volumes (annotated), 1954-1962 (Box 5)
    - 1955 (Box 6)
    - 1957
    - 1958
      - General
      - Larteguy, Jean, "Le Chef F.L.N. Yacef Saadi avait pris pour adjoint un colonel parachutiste" (The Head of the F.L.N., Yacef Saadi, mistook a French colonel for his cohort), Paris-Press L'Intransigeant, news clip and original typewritten draft (carbon copy) signed by Larteguy, April 8
      - L'Echo d'Alger, complete edition with headline "De Gaulle aux Algérois: 'Je vous ai compris'" (De Gaulle to the Algerians: "I have understood you"), June 5
    - 1959
    - 1960-1961
      - General
      - Procès de Barricades (Barricades Week Trial)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 7)
      - General
      - Susini, Jean-Jacques, "Nous l'O.A.S.," Minute, eight installments, 1963 October-November
    - 1970
    - 1971
    - 1972
    - 1974
      - Procès de Jean-Jacques Susini (Trial of Susini)
    - Undated
  - News journal (government) - Délégation Général du Gouvernement en Algérie, La Semaine en Algérie: Miroir de l'Algérie Française (The Week in Algeria: Mirror of French Algeria), nos. 22-35, 37-40, 42-44, 46-48, 50-69, 1958 December 15-1960 January 31 (Box 8)
  - Newsletters, privately circulated by exiles from Algeria, 1962-1963 (Box 9)
    - Nouvelles d'Algérie, 1962 November 15-30
    - Nouvelles d'Algérie, 1962 December 1-15
    - Nouvelles d'Algérie, 1962 December 15-1963 January 15
    - Nouvelles d'Algérie, 1963 January 15-February 1
    - Nouvelles d'Algérie, 1963 February
    - Vérités sur l'Algérie, 1963 March
    - Vérités sur l'Algérie, 1963 April
    - Cahiers Algériens, 1963 May
    - Cahiers Algériens, 1963 June-July
    - Untitled draft, possibly by Godard, circa 1963 August
  - Reports on the Operations of the Compagnie de Recherches et d'Exploration de Pétrole au Sahara, prepared for the inspection trip of General De Gaulle, 1958 December 5
  - Writings and notes of Yves Godard
    - "'Allo Carreras, ici Godard': Reflexions sur L'Accord FLN-OAS de Fernand Carreras" ("Hello Carreras, Godard Here": Thoughts on Fernand Carreras' L'Accord FLN-OAS), typewritten draft and carbon copy, each with holograph corrections, each 26 pages; holograph notes, 46 pages; holograph chronology for May-June 1962, 14 pages, circa 1967
    - "Barricades - 24 janvier 1960," typewritten and holograph manuscript draft on Barricades Week (January 24-29, 1960) in Algiers, 201 pages in note binder, undated
    - Card indexes (Box 10)
      - Chronological file, circa 1954-1962
      - Events and incidents file (événements), circa 1956-1957
      - Alphabetical file (collectivités), 1954-1958
      - Personalities file (fichier individual), circa 1954-1958
    - "Fichier 1960," holograph notes on individuals and organizations involved in events in Algeria from 1954-1960, 56 pages in note binder, undated (Box 11)
    - Notes and clippings on Algerian domestic and foreign affairs, holograph, 229 pages, 1964-1965
    - Notes and clippings on French domestic affairs, holograph, 148 pages, 1964-1965
    - Notes and clippings on French national defense, holograph, 195 pages, 1964-1965
    - Notes and clippings on repatriation, amnesty, arrests, trials, and other subjects affecting French Algerians, and in particular former members of the O.A.S., holograph, 79 pages, 1964-1965
    - Notes and documents on Barricades Week and the subsequent trial of the participants, handwritten notes and official summonses to appear as a witness, 1960 January-November
    - Trois Batailles d'Alger, 1972 (Box 12)
      - Outlines, notes, and chapter drafts, typewritten
      - Publisher's layout sheets of documents, photos and maps uses as illustrations
  - Miscellaneous
    - Notes, documents, and ephemera
    - Printed matter
      - Algérie développement, booklet printed for foreign distribution by the Délégation Générale du Gouvernement en Algérie, 1959
      - Algérie Médicale, special issue, medical journal containing articles on the problems of criminality and terrorism in Algeria, 1957
      - Algérie-Sahara: Guide touristique, commercial, industriel, guidebook, contains full-page photo of Godard, 1959
      - Aperçu sur l'Algérie, booklet distributed to military recruits from Metropolitan France assigned to Algeria, undated
      - Connaissance de l'Algérie, guidebook distributed by the Service Psychologique of the 10th Région Militaire
      - Guide Michelin: Algérie-Sahara, guidebook, 1956
      - Indicateur d'Alger, guidebook and map, 1964 (Box 13)
      - L'Indispensable, guidebook, contains full-page photo of Godard, 1959-1960
      - Kabaili, Le Grande Kabylie et ses problèmes, 1959
      - Pourquoi nous combattons, booklet published by the Conseil National de la Révolution, circa 1963
      - 15 mois d'action en Algérie, booklet published by the Gouvernement Général de l'Algérie, circa 1956
      - Soualah, Mohammed, Manuel Franco-Arabe à l'usage de militaires de l'Afrique du Nord, 4th edition, Algiers, 1953
      - Tableaux de l'économie algérienne, booklet published by the Statistique Générale de l'Algérie, 1958
      - U.A.P. (Union Africaine de Presse), special issue, photocopy of bulletin concerning Franco-Algerian negotiations, 1956-1958, 1961 February 23
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL (Box 14)
  - Maps of North Africa, Algeria, Algiers, Oran, Constantine, etc. (annotated); schematic plan of Algiers (annotated), circa 1954-1962
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Oversize photo file)